this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC radio net SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software this is Nate black for software
engineering radio my guest today is Ryan
singer Ryan is the head of product
strategy at Basecamp
he is the author of the book shape up
stop running in circles and ship work
that matters which explains base camps
software delivery process Ryan welcome
to software engineering radio hey there
thanks for having me
we had base camps CTO David henna Meyer
Hanson on the show in episode 216 to
talk about Ruby on Rails and he talked
about his thoughts on software
architecture and software design in this
episode it will be a little bit
different we're gonna be talking about
base camps approach to software
development methodology let's start by
talking about the book shape up is a
free ebook that describes your software
development methodology at Basecamp why
did you write shape up we had gone
through an internal process over the
course of the last few years of trying
to articulate what we had learned you
know as you go through the growing
process from being a tiny startup team
to bringing on more and more people you
go through these different phases where
you need to start to take on more
structure and you have to start to
articulate what you're doing you know
because in the beginning everybody just
kind of learns by osmosis and you know
the the founding team kind of has a
bunch of stuff in their gut and in their
intuition that you want to be able to to
turn into some sort of a structure that
other people can can repeat so we had to
figure out as we grew how to articulate
what we had been doing that that made
our product development process so
successful over the years especially
since we started working on Basecamp 3
in about 2015 we had more people on
board and and we just needed we needed
to actually kind of firm up how do
really explain all the things that we
have been doing that we're sort of
almost kind of a secret sauce for us and
then as we were going through that
process of sort of articulating to
ourselves you know what is what is
shaping what is betting what is uphill
and downhill work all these kind of
things we had lots of people continuing
to come to us you know friends and peers
from the outside saying how do you guys
do it and it felt like the right time to
do a book what do you see as being
really different from other
methodologies that are out there one
thing is the the pendulum swung too far
away from upfront design with agile what
we see looking out at a lot of other
teams is not enough decision-making at
the higher levels of the company and a
lot of decision-making getting pushed
down to the to the teams that are
building and too short of a time frame
where there's just two weeks at a time
two weeks at a time which makes it
really hard to to set a course where you
have a bigger vision of what you're
trying to accomplish and it makes it
hard to steer the product strategically
so we have more upfront design but we're
not swinging the pendulum back to
waterfall we're doing the right amount
of work on the work to figure out what
what the right work is so it's like we
we need to figure out what the teams are
going to do and what they're not going
to do and what the boundaries of the
solution are but we need to do that at
the right level of abstraction at the
right level of roughness so that we're
not giving the team a speck but we're
also not giving them something that's
too abstract and too fuzzy we need to
really set those guardrails on what we
think a solution is and then once we've
done that shaping work on what we think
the work is we're much more deliberate
about making bets so we don't just kind
of keep throwing time more and more time
and things and we don't allow things to
just keep running we define a clear
appetite upfront this is how much time
we intend to spend on this thing this is
how much time we think this thing is
worth and then we have a circuit breaker
in place so that if we spend more time
on something than we think it's worth
strategically we actually kill the
project and we can we can talk more
about that later so our approach to
betting is much more deliberate and then
finally when we're doing the building
the teams are actually executing the
work they are taking responsibility not
for tasks but for the entire project so
nobody's queuing up tasks for the team
or our stories or cards they have the
the the boundaries of the shaped work
and they are figuring out their own
tasks and discovering what the work is
for themselves inside those boundaries
and as they do that the focus isn't on
on velocity or or what's complete versus
what's incomplete the focus is on what's
known and unknown so we're really
focusing on risk and we want to make
sure that we sequence the problems in
the right order so that we're clear
about which things are solved in which
things are not solved because it's the
things that you think you're going to be
able to do but you haven't actually
solved yet that can really sink a
project and and drastically screw up
your you know the amount of time that
that you spend in the amount of time
that you have left so that's those are
some of the main ideas that are
different you don't have this backlog of
tasks that are assigned to people or in
fact there's no backlog at all could you
talk about that we don't have any kind
of a backlog and we see backlogs as
being a problematic in a lot of ways I
mean first of all it's it's it's just a
major drag to to have this big queue of
things that you're supposed to do that
you that you never get to for someone
who is in a position of actually making
decisions about you know what to do next
the backlog is just a portfolio of
options it's not it's not a terrible
thing but for all the other people who
are not actually in the position of
making that call the backlog feels like
a bunch of stuff that we're supposed to
do that that we haven't gotten to and on
top of it the backlog becomes the place
that work goes when we don't agree so if
we're not actually going to do something
then we just say okay we'll throw it on
the backlog so then the backlog becomes
this big credibility problem you know
you say that you're gonna put it there
instead of saying no to it but then but
then you never get to it so there's sort
of a mixed message there and it just
becomes a big weight on everybody's
shoulders and and it's all old stuff so
what we want to do instead is we want to
be more thoughtful about a few things
that are contextual and timely and
relevant so we have the
betting table so we're working in we're
not working in two-week sprints were
working in six weeks cycles and between
the six weeks cycles we have a two-week
cooldown period and in this cool-down we
have what we call a betting table and
that's where the people who are in a
position to decide how we spend our time
evaluate a few options to decide what to
do next and what they're looking at
isn't a long backlog of old stuff the
only way that something gets to a
betting table is if a person personally
brings it to the table and advocates for
it and the work that's getting brought
to the table are potential bets so this
is work that's been shaped work that
somebody spent time figuring out
outlining identifying the major risks
figuring out the major technical issues
that are going to be a factor doing the
the sort of the key tentpoles of the
design so there's there's work that's
being brought to the table that's
already kind of roughly solved in terms
of the boundaries of the work and
somebody's bringing that saying this is
the right time for this and this is
important right now and this is the
thing that that I think we should do
next so instead of having a big queue of
things you've got maybe three or four
things at the table that are really
thought out and are the right things for
what's going on in the company right now
and then that's a much deeper more
productive conversation than it would be
with just kind of trying to groom a big
old list of things what's going on
during the six weeks of the cycle I
think you said there are two tracks what
are what are the tracks and what's going
on in those tracks you know when you're
really small the people who do the
shaping and figure out what the work is
and the people who build the work all
need to be the same people you know if
you're just a team of three or four I
mean you you you have to wear all the
hats and you just have to alternate rows
roles and you work in a kind of ad hoc
way that doesn't work once you once you
get to a bigger size at our current size
now we're about maybe like a dozen
people on the product team and fifty and
the overall company and so we're big
enough that we can have some people like
myself and in Jason the founder working
on shaping what to do and we can do that
on a different track from the teams that
are actually building out prod
so there's a sort of a shaping track
where we're figuring out what the work
is and kind of forming up potential bets
and then there's a building track where
teams of one designer and one or two
programmers take something that was
shaped and they work out what that
actual design and implementation looks
like and and they ship that within the
six weeks and the place where these two
meet
they crossover in the in the in the at
the betting table so in the two week
cooldown between the six week cycles
we're we're looking at the work that was
shaped and it could be something that
just was just shaped yesterday or it
could be something that's been sitting
since you know since six weeks ago or
something that we revived you know
there's no strictness about that it's
just whatever is timely and we'll look
at a few options and then if we think
that this is the right time to bet time
and resources on an idea then that'll go
to a team in the next six weeks to build
okay and that idea of first determining
your appetite or a time budget for the
project and then making the project fit
I think is what you label fixed time
variable scope yeah and we're of course
we're not the first ones to talk about
fixed time variable scope that goes back
to at least two extreme programming you
know a lot of the the basic principle
there is is informed by by stuff like
that so you know some of your listeners
of course are going to know about Kent
Beck's work and all of that but the
difference is that this is not a just
within the context of programmers we're
not just talking about like an
engineering team we're stepping all the
way back to what we could call you know
people are calling quote-unquote product
today which is we're looking at the
strategy and the design and the
technical implementation all together
and figuring out what it is that we want
to do and how much time we want to spend
on that so we're not just doing fixed
time variable scope for a technical
implementation we're actually thinking
what do we want to do in terms of the
whole product concept when you have a
smaller team that's responsible for both
shaping and building they're not going
back and forth and having a discussion
and then going back to their desk and
building there's still I think this
operation where the the shaping part is
continuing to happen until you have
something that's shaped enough that then
you send it off to be built yeah or you
give it to yourself to build and then
you just change hats okay but there's
still this separation in terms of you
wouldn't start building it until the
beginning of a new cycle that depends on
on your size again I actually don't
think that cycles and in our experience
cycles strict cycles don't make a lot of
sense when you're very very small if
you're only three or four people and you
kind of all do everything then you can
be very ad hoc with how you manage your
time together if a communication cost is
very low it's not complex to figure out
who's available and what's possible you
can just drop something in the chat and
then immediately change course because
you have such a tiny ship together you
know so when we were smaller we didn't
have to to adhere to six week cycles and
two-week cooldowns we could just say hey
let's do this for the next two weeks
okay we don't know what we're doing yet
we're doing some shaping okay now we're
good how about for the next three weeks
we do this thing and it could be a
different unit of time didn't have to be
repeating the exact same unit all that
sort of a thing the issue is that once
you have more people then managing the
capacity in itself becomes a big
challenge you know there's just too many
people to figure out who's available and
what is everybody gonna work on so you
need some more regularity and some more
structure in order to operate at that
scale so we introduced the strict six
weeks after we after we had gotten
bigger you know than that than that
original tiny team are there any
guidelines for recommendations you have
for people to decide when to impose the
structure or is it just a matter of
feeling when things are starting to get
hard to manage I think the general rule
is that all of the things that people do
at larger scales hurt you at smaller
scales so very often we look up to two
big companies and we think well I should
do it like them because they're
successful and they're a bigger company
but when we're small we have luxuries
that we don't have when we're bigger you
know just being able to wave your hand
and say hey everybody let's just do this
other thing for the next couple weeks
instead or you know we don't have
be fixed to six weeks let's do let's
let's just do three weeks for this thing
and then move on that's a luxury and
being able to also share all of that
context between the people who shape and
the people who build if you're the same
people I mean you can do incredible work
when you're small enough to do that
so I think the general principle is do
what smaller teams do as long as as long
as possible until stuff starts to break
and then when stuff is actually breaking
around you or you're feeling pain and
you're struggling because you can't wing
it anymore
only then should you start to impose the
extra structure that makes sense
let's talk more about shaping and really
go into detail on that where would you
like to start with shaping what what
what is shaping we touched on a little
bit so shaping is the transition from
how do we get from a raw idea that is
just like you know quote-unquote build a
calendar or the customer wants X or the
founder came up with this idea yesterday
you know whatever it is how do we get
from that to something that is a good
potential bet with more risk removed
where we can say okay we know what it
means to build this thing so there's a
few phases that we go through then to do
this shaping work the first thing is we
have to set the boundaries so you know
what happens is somebody will say oh you
know the customer says they want to have
categories on the message section and
then everybody says oh you know I heard
about that too but maybe we could
redesign it so that we could have a new
organization side bar and then before
you know it there's this sort of out of
control conversation about you know
redesigning everything and before that
happens
you want to step back and say to
yourself well wait a minute how how big
is this problem how meaningful is it for
us strategically how much time is it
worth how far do we want to go here so
you know it's natural of course to want
to build the best best best of whatever
you can come up with but the constraints
change the definition of what good is so
objectively a steak dinner is better
than a hotdog but if you only have five
minutes the hotdog ism is the better
choice you know and so we're looking at
as ideas come up we want to start off
by defining what we call the appetite
how much time do we want to spend on
this how interesting is it how much does
it matter so something can come up like
the calendar for example we were getting
this customer request repeatedly for
Basecamp three saying please build a
calendar view into Basecamp three and we
did not want to do it because we had
built calendars before and we built a
pretty good one in Basecamp two and it
took us like six months to do it and we
thought man we do not want to do that
again so we and we also knew that only
about 10% of customers used it so we
were saying to ourselves we don't want
to do that but we of course want to make
our customers happy and we are getting
this request so if there's something we
could do that was more like a six-week
sized project then we'd be open to that
so that's that's defining the appetite
now you've set some boundaries and those
boundaries are constraining the solution
space so if we can't come up with some
kind of a six-week sized calendar or
what it means to build a calendar that
would be meaningful in six weeks we
don't know how to move further down the
shaping process yet right because we're
just sort of like well I don't wanna
know how to do that in six weeks we
might need to do more problem definition
then to give ourselves more constraints
to to find the right place in the
solution space so what we did in this
case was we interviewed some customers
who were asking about this calendar and
we kind of backtracked to unpack what
was going on for them when they made the
request and what exactly they were
struggling with so we could figure out
what mattered about about about a
calendar and eventually when we did that
we came to a point where we had kind of
a really really basic ride like a rough
concept of what a simple calendar would
mean and all the things that don't
matter for this problem and we were able
to catch just in a fat marker on a white
board here's here's the concept I think
this is something we could do in six
weeks and it would scratch the itch
based on this is our appetite this is
our understanding of the problem and
this is now our sort of rough idea of
what the solution is once we've got that
then we actually have kind of an idea to
bring to the table we've got something
we think we can do that is is worth the
amount of time and we think that it's
feasible but very often the people who
are shaping shaping is a sort of
integration beat
what is strategically meaningful and
design skill so you've got to be able to
look at it from the customer point of
view and and sketch out something that
is that is drawn out in user facing
terms of course if you're doing that as
somebody who's a little bit more leaning
toward the design side there might be
things that you don't understand about
the technical implementation or there
might be things about the way that there
are interdependencies in the existing
system or it might just be you know more
complicated than you think
and so in order to be in the shaping
world you need to have enough technical
literacy to not be way off the map you
know about feasibility and and what's
doable in what amount of time but
there's still going to be a depth of
understanding that you might not have
that somebody who's deeply technical has
so then we go from from this kind of you
know imagine sort of two people in a
room with the door closed on a
whiteboard with a lot of shared context
just kind of jamming out spread boarding
ideas we talked about bread boarding in
the book it's sort of a notation system
that allows us to move at the right at
the right speed and without getting lost
in too much detail we're kind of jamming
on the whiteboard together we're like
aha okay this is this is gonna work Oh
awesome yeah what about this uh-huh okay
so it's like this like super intense
collaborative mode out of that we get
some kind of a concept and then and
we're gonna change modes and we're gonna
need to actually share this with a few
people who are more technical than we
are to get pushback on it so this is
what we call like de-risking or looking
for the rabbit holes so we're gonna take
the concept to a couple trusted
technical people and we're gonna redraw
it in front of them kind of from start
to end on the whiteboard and we're gonna
say here's what we're thinking you're
gonna go from here to here to here and
we're gonna connect this and connect
that and that's how we're gonna do the
job and then the technical person can
push back on you and say yeah but what
about this what about that that's not
quite as simple as you think you know
and and they're gonna help you to sort
of sort of harden the concepts and then
if you need to you can go back into the
earlier shaping phase where you're kind
of recon cepting in response to that or
it might be that you just get all of
your questions answered and you're able
to really button up the thing so after
we've gone through sort of setting the
boundaries doing the shaping of actually
coming up with the concept and then
looking for those rabbit holes and
de-risking it then the last step of
shaping is if we get to a point where
all this is making sense then we can
write it up as a pitch and the pitch
sort of summarizes all this work that
we've done here's our appetite
here's up understanding of the problem
here's the broad outlines of the
solution here's a very rough sketch of
what we think this looks like here's the
rabbit holes that we've identified or
our answer to the technical questions
that are going to come up and then this
is the potential bet this is something
we could take to the betting table and
then lobby for and compare against other
options to see if it's something we're
going to do you talk about fat marker
sketches yeah you're not really going
into a high-resolution detailed
description about what's going on in
fact there's no kind of wireframes that
are being made or detailed design in
shaping but any of that detailed stuff
would actually be done later into
implementation phase yes we do not want
to fall back into making some kind of a
detailed spec you know we don't know
enough up front to to spec every little
detail it would be a waste of our time
because of course we would find out on
day three of the actual project that
that everything we thought was gonna
work out a certain way isn't right but
that doesn't mean that we don't do any
upfront design so it's all about doing
the design at the right level of
abstraction so we need we need to be at
that level where it's rough enough that
we're leaving a lot of latitude for the
team to actually work out what the real
details and the fine-grained decisions
look like but it also there has to be
enough structure there at a course level
so that we know that what it is and we
know what it's not and so the bread
boarding in the fat marker sketches kind
of help us to work at that right level
of abstraction
can you explain bread boarding bread
boarding is a metaphor from Electrical
Engineering you know if you're if you're
tinkering with electronics you don't
want to have to solder a board just to
try out an idea you know because that's
that's difficult to undo and then you
have to throw the board away when you're
done if you want to if you have to
solder all the components with a
breadboard you have you know this little
plastic thing with some contacts to to
easily connect the different leads of
your different components to power and
you can just plug and unplug a few
component
to see if you turn the switch on if the
circuit does what you think it's going
to do or not and so it's it's allowing
you to prototype the connectivity
between components to see if the thing
does what you think it's going to do and
you're not making any industrial design
decisions you know you're not choosing
the the color and material of the
chassis or or placing the switch you
know how many millimeters from the left
or from the top you're just wiring
everything together and it's kind of a
mess of wires and you're plugging and
unplugging things but it allows you to
quickly prototype is this the right way
to get from A to B and and kind of if I
connect all these things in this way
does the circuit work or not so we can
really think of a software design as a
circuit in the sense that you have to be
able to get from the beginning to the
end and everything has to flow in an
uninterrupted way so that you can
actually execute the tasks that you need
to do bread boarding is a way to quickly
cover a lot of ground when you're
thinking through some kind of a user
facing interaction and some kind of a
flow that happens in the software if we
had to draw wireframes then we get
dragged down into the wrong level of
detail anytime we are figuring out you
know if this should be on the left or
the right or above or below we're too
far down we're too far down in the weeds
and what we want instead is to focus on
what are the affordances what are the
places where the affordances go not in
terms of you know X Y position on the
screen but in terms of almost more
topologically like it's it belongs on
this step so the dashboard is going to
have a button that says add invoice now
it doesn't have to be on the left or the
right but it sits in that place and then
from there if you click that it takes
you to this other place called the add
invoice screen and on that place are
these affordances right so it allows us
to very very very quickly sketch out an
idea and and cover a lot of surface area
where we can see exactly kind of what
the interface is doing but we're not
actually looking at a visual layout and
so that gives us both the the latitude
that we need so we're not boxing the
team into a specific design and it also
gives us the sort of speed that we need
so that when we are actually exploring
different ideas for what the solution
is we can cover a lot of ground really
fast without getting bogged down so at
the end of the shaping process you would
have put together a pitch which I think
would consist of something about the
problem statement these fad marker
sketches breadboards some kind of
document could you explain what the
pitch looks like and then what we do
with that in terms of bringing it to the
betting table yeah all we're trying to
do with the pitch is take everything
together that we would need to share
this concept with somebody who doesn't
have all the context that we had you
know so for example if if you start to
if you start to present an idea for this
quick-and-dirty sort option that you're
gonna add to this you know forum feature
what can easily happen you've probably
had these conversations before you're
trying to pitch the quick and dirty
version and then somebody else is
pointing out all the faults of your
quick and dirty version and they're
describing a much deeper version that's
better right and this is where whenever
you have a kind of committee situation
the scope just runs out of control
because everybody's trying to make it
better and nobody's talking about the
constraints so the main thing that the
pitch needs to do is it needs to present
your idea of what to do as a solution
but it has to present the constraints at
the same time so that way if you say to
everybody look a very small percentage
of customers are reporting this issue we
don't believe this affects a lot of
people but it's a little bit of a
disproportionate load on support so if
we can come up with something to fix
this problem and just let's say two
weeks we're willing to do it but if it
takes longer than that this doesn't
affect enough people and we've got
bigger fish to fry then everybody can
say aha okay
we've all got ideas for how this could
be better but we understand why the
appetite is only two weeks so now we can
evaluate all of the trade-offs that were
made to get to this kind of compromised
scope that's good enough to scratch the
itch given what it's worth so that's the
kind of context that we need to put into
the pitch so that people can properly
evaluate it and then what we're doing
with that is we're taking that to the
betting table and kind of who what the
betting table is and who it is
we can't be overly prescriptive here
because companies are of different size
and they have sort of slightly different
org structures and everything like that
but basically there's somebody in your
organization who gets to decide how
programmers and designers spend their
time and what we want to do is that
person or those people who have the
power to make that decision we want to
align those resources of designer and
programmers together into integrated
teams so we're gonna have teams of one
designer and one or two programmers and
we want to be able to give those teams
want a piece of work that's been shaped
so that they have the best odds of being
successful because they know what to do
and what not to do and how far to go and
where to stop and what done more or less
looks like given the amount of time that
we're betting and so we need to have the
people who can make that decision plus
whoever's been doing the shaping needs
to be able to sort of you know lobby for
and defend whatever it is that they
shaped and then depending on the case
you may have a couple other people
around to to sort of advice or chime in
or debate so that this is kind of a
negotiation about what what is the right
thing to do next and so the pitch then
is a potential bet that somebody might
choose to bring to the table for a given
cycle to say this I think is the thing I
want to lobby for us to do in the next
cycle I think there's a built-in
assumption that there's always more work
that could be done than the amount of
time and resources available to do it ya
think pets tends to be true so what
you're doing is you're just trying to
narrow the scope of the decision down to
you just the work that's gone through
the shaping process so that's
well-defined enough that you could be
successful in implementing it and that
you could also make a determination hey
like this will really make a difference
it's important that we do this work and
it's defined enough that that we can we
can actually start working on it because
that upfront shaping works already have
been finished
yeah and it's a skin in the game process
if you put a bunch of stuff on a backlog
everybody has to look at it again why
just because it's the backlog said so
the backlog doesn't get to say anything
it's just it's just a list people should
have to lobby for things if I want
something to happen then I need to
remember that thing and bring it to the
table and say I think this thing is
important there's no there's no list
that's going to
that for us in that way there's an
automatic selection function that's
that's winnowing everything down because
we only have limited amount of time and
attention and people actually have to
choose something for themselves to bring
to the table to advocate for why do you
call it betting versus planning what's
the key distinction so when you plan you
say this is what's going to happen and
that is using the language of certainty
and with betting we're actually using
the language of risk so bets have some
different properties than plans do so
the first thing with a bet is you have a
when you make a bet you bet a fixed
amount and that means that there's a cap
on your downside you should never bet a
certain amount and then when the moment
of truth comes have to pay more than
that that doesn't make any sense but
that's what we do all the time in
software projects you know too often you
say let's spend two weeks on that and
then of course it doesn't work the way
that you expected and then you throw
another two weeks in another two weeks
and then before you know it you don't
even know how much time you spent on it
compared to what you originally wanted
to that doesn't make any sense so we we
put in place what we call the circuit
breaker this means if we bet on a
certain amount of weeks for a team of
designer and programmers to do and they
don't finish within that period of time
it's over they don't automatically get
any more time to do that thing because
that time that thing wasn't worth more
time and who knows what has come up in
the meantime we might have a much better
there might be something urgent that
just came up there might be a great new
opportunity we just identified who knows
there could be a lot of other things so
we shouldn't be beholden to that old
thing just because it took too long that
doesn't make it worth the extra time so
so that's the first thing is that bets
have a capped downside and we can
enforce that with the circuit breaker
the second thing is when you make a bet
you have some sort of a payoff in mind
of you know why you're making the bet
and what you hope to get out of it and
we've done that with the shaping work so
we should have we shouldn't just give
something to a team and say peck at it
and see how far you get we're betting on
a specific piece of shaped work there's
a certain outcome and a definition of
what done looks like that we are hoping
to get out of that bet and then the
third thing is that if
you make a bet then you have to honor it
and what it means to to honor the bet is
that if we give the team let's say six
weeks to build this particular piece of
shape work we have to actually give them
to six weeks giving them the six weeks
means we don't interrupt them so we
don't go and tongue it tug at their
shoulder and say hey can you can you
just do this other thing instead today
or we just had this one thing come up
can we can you help me with that
or whatever it is we don't interrupt the
team not only do we not interrupt the
team with other work we also don't
interrupt the team with stupid meetings
that destroy their productivity so we
don't have daily stand-ups we don't have
regularly scheduled meetings of any kind
instead we give the team the room to
work on things for the right amount of
period the right amount of time that
they need in order to before they raise
a hand or or gather together to decide
what to do next you know the structure
of work the actual problems that you
need to solve and the things that you
have to build to get the software to do
what it needs to do this structure is
highly irregular it's much more like a
like a like an organism or like like an
animal
skeleton than it is like some it's not
some kind of a periodic crystal it's not
like the work doesn't come in in day
size chunks or week size chunks there's
there's a problem you have to work on
for three days and then and then you get
it solved and then you work on something
else for for two hours and it's solved
right and then you work on something for
one day and it's solved and then you
have a thing for like six days that you
work on right so this irregularity means
that the team needs to be able to decide
when is the right time to meet when is
the right time to get help and that kind
of a thing so we really we leave the
team alone for the whole six weeks and
then they have the the actual amount of
time that we bet on to execute the thing
I think we touched on this a little bit
earlier but what you're saying is
there's no task level assignment at all
there's no definition at the planning
phase of the tasks or who's going to do
them or anything like that we don't know
any of that upfront you know every time
we try to say these are the tasks first
of all it's disempowering you know then
you your
juicing the team - ticket takers and
code monkeys and grunt workers if you
just give them a cue to work off of all
the time but second of all there's a
there's also an epistemological issue we
just don't know upfront what the real
specific tasks are and if somebody tries
to play architect at that level of scale
that's the wrong level to do it there
it's just going to blow up in our faces
as soon as we encounter the reality so
we're working with the grain of how
things really are we can do upfront
planning at a higher level of
abstraction where we say more or less
this is the design concept and these are
the main technical tent poles that we
expect you know but when it comes to the
actual work the fine grain work we can't
predict that up front so it's better for
the team to have the latitude to to
discover and and capture their own tasks
during the six weeks what it's the
composition of the building team very
simple we've got one designer and one or
two programmers depending on the size of
the work that's it and then toward the
end of the project we'll have a QA
person come in but the QA is is not a
gate it's not a check point that all the
work has to go through for some kind of
acceptance or something like that rather
we expect the designers and programmers
to build perfectly shippable work that
does what it's supposed to do and then
we reached a certain size where you know
small compatibility issues on different
types of browsers or devices can
multiply in absolute numbers to quite a
few affected people and then all it
takes is a few dozen reports something
in support and it feels like a big issue
even though you know relatively speaking
it's not so we found it valuable to have
this QA person come in to sort of as an
extra as an extra level of help to find
the kinds of things that that the team
wouldn't have time to find so it's
really about edge cases and tricky
things it's not about the core
functionality but that's it
it's just the designers the programmers
and then a little bit of QA at the end
that's the team could you talk about
what the building process looks like in
particular how do how does it get
started how do you get the ball rolling
yeah so
because the team doesn't have a list of
tasks that's been assigned to them the
very first few days of the project or
gonna look like there's no work
happening from the outside because the
team has to get familiar with the pitch
they have to get familiar with the the
lay of the land of the existing system
you know does this connect to that the
way I think it is you know how does this
work currently that's sort of a thing so
there's a period of getting oriented and
starting to sketch out approaches so
right away from the beginning the
designer is going to be identifying some
core piece of work - to start stubbing
out and the designers goal is not to
produce a pixel perfect mock-up and then
hand that to a to a to a developer
instead of that the designer is actually
going to be just stubbing in the
essential affordances again that need to
be there because what is a programmer
need a programmer doesn't need a font or
a decision about the color blue really
that the programmers need to know what
what are the end points in the interface
that I have to wire together so that it
does something you know so the first cut
of the interface for a specific chunk of
the work can really just be some fields
and some buttons and some text that is
is just enough to functionally afford
the process without all the visual
styling and and the final decisions
about you know this color blue and on
the left or on the right that kind of a
thing and so while the designer is
getting started on the first piece of
design like that there's enough
information in the shaped work in the
pitch for the programmers to to be
thinking about you know what's the right
way to model this in the backend what's
the what if we're gonna be making
changes to the database what's the right
way to start to think about this so
there's they're they're already being
productive even though they don't have
design yet and then the goal is that by
the end of the first week or maybe the
very beginning of the second week the
designer has put together enough design
for one specific chunk of the of the
work hooked it up in a rough way and
then the the programmers are you know
connecting that to controller actions or
wiring it back to the to the to the
model or whatever they need to do and
there's something that you can click on
so we're integrating early on one chunk
of the work both front end and back end
that we could kind of slice orthogonal E
apart from the rest of the work that
needs to get done and that first piece
of work should be of course not just the
thing that you've done a hundred times
before so you don't of course you know
you don't start with the login screen
you start with something that is of
interest in the domain and that will
teach you something because it's
something that you haven't exactly built
before you know you want to start
working on something that has enough
interdependency with the other problems
you're going to encounter later that as
you tug on that string
you know it's teaching you about how all
the problems are connected to each other
so so that's how the team starts they
there's a little bit of radio silence at
first as they get oriented the designer
is focusing on the affordances over the
it's not a pixel perfect design yet and
they're there the team is scoping out
one chunk of the work that's that's
valuable that they can integrate and get
to a point where you can actually click
on it on a beta server very early in the
process like by the end of the first
week is there an example that comes to
mind or maybe one from your book about
that would illustrate things that you
leave out versus things that you would
focus on as you're trying to get that
one piece done the main thing to do is
is to just have this clear split in your
mind of make it work before you make it
pretty and and most teams even agile
teams that are supposedly not supposed
to be doing this are basically just
doing high-frequency waterfall where a
designer makes something all the way to
full fidelity and you hand it over to a
developer and then they implement it and
you repeat you repeat and we're doing
the opposite of that we just need to get
the components to click together so that
I fill in this form field and I click
this button and it takes me to the next
screen and it says saved or it shows me
whatever I need to see next and it's
like look it works that's the victory
moment that's the point where we're kind
of over the hill and we don't have
uncertainty anymore about whether this
is viable then when you've done that now
you can layer in you know extra style
you can play with the presentation of it
there might be some more refactoring to
do there might be more edge cases to
support but it's really about just
getting them getting those bones in
getting the integration between what are
the main UI elements and then
and I click on them so they actually do
something that's that's that's where we
want to focus at first okay so that the
first version might just be it might
just look like unstyled HTML but you
could click on something and it would
actually make the desired change in your
database exactly the end of the day it's
from n2 and from top to bottom exactly
right so we if we kind of a picture the
work as a as a you know two horizontal
layers a back-end layer and then of and
then a UI layer on top we want to take
that PI in slices and do vertical slices
where there's a little bit of UI and a
little bit of back-end together and then
that then we've got something real if we
just do a whole bunch of back-end first
and then we think that all of this is
going to be useful for us later then
we're doing speculative work and it's
not going to connect the way we think if
we do a whole bunch of UI first then the
same thing we've done a whole bunch of
work but none of it actually does
anything but if we do just a little bit
of UI and a little bit of back-end if we
wire them together then there's no doubt
that we accomplished something that is
going to stay in the codebase and it's
going to get shipped at the end you know
we've we've actually accomplished
something the the universe of unsolved
problems has shrunk because we can
actually say here's a part of the
problem that we don't have to think
about anymore you talk about scopes and
scope mapping in the book our scopes
those slices of the pie yes exactly
right so you can't see all of the scopes
upfront because what we've got with the
shaped work is we have a kind of fence
around the perimeter of some work that's
to be figured out but then the the
interior of that fenced off area is like
a wilderness it's like a place you've
never been and you have to walk that
territory to actually figure out what
it's going to take to do and what the
interdependencies are and and and what
the structure of the problem is so you
can't you can't just map everything out
up front but as you start to build out
the first you kind of pick a central
scope that you think is worthwhile to do
first and as you start to work on that
you're going to bump into all kinds of
other things you know how it is you you
get in the code and you think that
you're trying to add a method to this
class over here and then
while you're there you already realize
like oh but this thing also calls that
other thing from here I'm gonna have to
make a note of that right so you're
actually building knowledge of the
interdependencies in the system as you
kind of wander around even just trying
to do that very first thing but then
what happens is you get the first thing
built you kind of take on the next thing
and then you've bumped into enough by
maybe the end of the first maybe by the
second week that you can start to map
that territory and you can start to say
okay of all the things that we need to
do to fulfill this concept that was
shaped there's basically these maybe
three or four main areas that we could
sort of treat orthogonal E and then and
and then you can kind of draw out these
different scopes and you can say aha
okay we treat naming scopes the way that
a good programmer treats naming objects
and functions and and namespaces and
stuff like that naming is hard but
naming is really really important
because it gives you the ability to
start to string sentences together with
the different pieces of the problems to
you so we you know for example we had
this project where we were building
permissions for clients using base camp
and the Scopes broke out into some
things that had very specific terms like
bucket access recording visibility you
know things like that and these had a
specific meaning to the team that was
working on them and then they could say
let's get bucket access to the point
where it's firm and then we can we can
go back to styling the recording toggle
you know and then there they're sort of
speaking the language of the project and
they're being very deliberate about
which problems they're working on at
what time and then they can they can do
that technique we talked about earlier
kind of again and again and again where
there's enough back end on this scope
there's enough front end on this scope
where we say AHA that one is more or
less solved we don't need to worry about
that so much so now maybe instead of
taking that all the way to full polish
let's shift gears and work on this other
scope because there's some scary
unknowns in it you know so this is where
they're mapping the territory and
they're also kind of roving around and
they're being very intentional about how
far they build up the different layers
within each scope he also gave some
examples of poorly defined scopes and
some signs of poorly designed scopes
I think one is that they're just not
named well or they're what you call a
grab bag is that right or is this that
is that the level of the project there's
a few signs to tell you if the scopes
are right or if they're not right it's
generally a smell if a scope has a
generic name if your scope isn't domain
specific and it's like something like
front end you know front end or bugs or
something like that that is that's a
grab bag like you said the issue with a
scope called front end is you never know
when you're done you know it's not
carving front end is a horizontal cut
it's not a vertical cut so what we want
to do is we want to make we want to make
vertical cuts that tell us when this
part of the problem is done so instead
of front end we want to have store reply
trash send you know things like that and
then within those vertical slices then
we integrate both front end and back end
tasks so that's that's one smell another
smell is if the scope is too big then
it's not helping it's not helping you
you know if if a scope takes longer than
a week to do it basically becomes a
project you know and and the whole
notion of a scope is that we should have
a chunk of the work that we can carve
out from the rest and integrate over and
and then the universe of our problems
has shrunk it should be relatively
relatively small and it should be
something that we need to be able to we
need to be able to see what what done
looks like for it
you know and and assign a sign that the
scope is right is the scope start to act
like buckets for the tasks that you
discover so we talked about imagined
versus discovered tasks you know and as
the team is working and bumping into
things and finding things that they're
gonna have to do later
if the scopes actually course - - the
anatomy of the work and they reflect the
the parts that are orthogonal from each
other and as tasks come up you're
actually gonna be able to bucket them
inside that scope and say ah okay that's
actually about recording visibility you
know that's about bucket access that's
about trashing or whatever right and in
this way the work always has a place to
go and it's easier to kind of have
conversations about the work because you
have a kind of large-scale straw
sure that's telling you kind of what you
have to do and it's not just a giant
pile of tasks you had two different
methods of showing progress so you said
in the book that teams don't like being
interrupted
for progress updates all the time but
managers and decision makers also don't
like constantly asking for progress it's
kind of yeah nobody likes it nobody
likes it so you you have actually two
different tools that you use one our
to-do lists and the other are the hill
chart could you explain what the to-do
lists and Hill charts look like in your
system yeah so of course we have to
capture tasks we have to know what to do
you know and if we're not going to queue
those up in some kind of you know list
in advance for people then what are we
going to do so the way that we handle
this is the teams start off with just
discovering some tasks that they think
they're going to have to do because like
I said you can't see all the scopes from
day one because you have to walk the
territory before you can map it so in
the beginning there's just going to be a
kind of a loose set of tasks that aren't
really scoped that are just a bunch of
sort of key things that the team has
identified that they're gonna have to do
then as you start to to work on a
specific scope and you start to map
things out then it becomes natural to
aggregate these tasks per scope so the
way we do this in Basecamp is we have a
project the teams working inside of a
Basecamp project that Basecamp project
has a to-do section in it and that to do
section allows you to to group to dues
together into lists and so the team will
name the lists after the scopes that
they've found so they'll create if they
have a scope that's called you know
let's say they're working on some kind
of a messaging feature and there's a
there's there's a delivery aspect to it
there might be a scope called deliver or
send and and that scope might include
some UI that needs to happen for
different states of successfully sending
or updating to say that it was delivered
or whatever and then of course there's
going to be back-end issues with
actually performing the delivery so
those tasks might go together in a list
called send and then if new things come
up and have to do with that work then
you just keep adding tasks to that list
and then you've got other lists that
named after the other scopes so that's
basically kind of how do we bucket the
work how do we capture the work and how
does the team know where to put the work
as they go so that they have a kind of
clear way to deal with with sort of
there's more work over here on this
issue and and and this thing came up but
I'm not going to deal with it yet but I
I know where to put it over there so so
the the work is captured in lists and
the lists correspond to scopes
that is just so that stuff doesn't get
lost you know and it also enables the
conversation about the work because
people can discuss back and forth in the
comments on a particular task you know
the the details of the work but that's
really just about capture and not losing
things
when it comes to showing progress we
have this other tool called the hill
chart and we've actually kind of been
talking about it in a way so far we
talked about this notion that you reach
a point where the UI is stubbed out and
you've you can see exactly kind of okay
I'm going to wire this to this and this
this and that and the controller and
this is where it connects in the model
and is that API where I think it is
let's see uh-huh yep it is okay so that
connects with the way I think and okay
this looks like it's gonna work you
reach a point where all of your unknowns
are gone but you're still not done and
we use the metaphor of climbing a hill
you know when you're climbing up a steep
hill you can't see the top until you get
to the top but then when you get to the
top and you can see down all sides and
and you can see everything so the early
phase of a scope is where you're
figuring out kind of wedding what is the
exact approach do these different pieces
of the system connect the way that I
think that they do if we wire this
together are we gonna like it the way we
think we're gonna like it you know so
there's this this work that you do to
sort of figure out what is the actual
approach how do things connect together
is it going to work the way that you
expect and you're doing just the minimum
amount of stubbing and spiking to
validate that but then you reach a point
where you say yeah this is this is
figured out but there's still execution
work left so that's what it's like to be
at the top of the hill you can see
everything else that you need to get
done so I like to use sometimes the
analogy of if you're building a piece of
IKEA furniture there's a big difference
between what
a little bunch of parts lying on the
floor and you're like alright I don't
know if this is gonna be twenty minutes
or three hours right but then there's a
different point where it's kind of
standing and you've got four screws in
your hand and you're looking at and you
can see four holes and you say okay I
have work left but I have very little
uncertainty about this work right it's a
different risk regime and the way that
we think about risk is very binary
either it's solved and you are 100%
certain this you are going to be able to
finish this thing and it's going to work
or it's not solved and an unknown could
bite us and if an unknown bites us and
something doesn't click together we
think it's going to or there's something
about the way that it works in the UI
that isn't satisfactory if there's
something that we don't solve it might
take a day to solve it it might take
another week to solve it or it might it
might take six months before we have a
Eureka or it might actually be
unsolvable given the way the existing
system works and that is a that is that
is a huge risk so so we're viewing the
uphill part of the work as getting all
that risk out getting to the point where
we are sure about it and then we can
believe that the thing is going to be
okay and it's going to get into the
final ship product and then the downhill
work is just the remaining execution so
on a per scope basis we have this hill
chart and we can draw a dot that
corresponds to each scope to show where
it is on the hill and the teams just
drag this on the hill and this is
totally from the stomach it's not some
artificial velocity point estimation
blah blah blah it's not some made-up
number that people don't even know what
it means it is right from the gut
reflecting where are you in terms of
known and unknown on this specific piece
of work from getting your hands dirty
and actually being involved in it you
know and then by looking at that hill
chart this is something that the teams
can update asynchronously it's actually
fun you know when you get to a point
where you solve something and then you
you you drag that dot up to the top of
the hill and you're like look that's
that's figured out that's that's kind of
a moment to celebrate or if all work
actually starts at the very very far
bottom-left of the hill even if you
think you know what to do head work
isn't the same thing as opening up the
hood and and confirming that those end
points are where they think there they
are
that that method takes the arguments you
think it does or whatever it is so it
can also happen that you you have an
idea about what your approach is you get
in there into the code and you say
uh-huh
that's where I think it is and you drag
yourself up a quarter of the way up the
hill and you say look I've validated
some of my assumptions you know and then
so the team is kind of celebrating their
progress and showing that they're
getting somewhere by updating the hill
and then at the same time someone who is
outside of the team who's interested in
in how they're doing this could be
somebody who's a bit more in a product
manager type role who's wondering if if
the project is going successfully or not
or it could be somebody who is in maybe
more of a sort of a performance
evaluation role so maybe there's a more
senior programmer that these programmers
report to and this person is it wants to
know if this programmer is kind of
what's the what's the what's the rate of
their problem solving you know I mean
are they getting somewhere or they stuck
or how's that going and then they
regardless of the case either either
those people could just take a look at
that hill chart again asynchronously
and they can see if work is moving up
and over the hill or not and they can
even see at what speed on the second
order because Basecamp actually allows
you to see snapshots of the hill over
time so you can see today versus three
days ago
you know what's moved and this gives a
really good sense of what problems is
the team solving and are they stuck or
are they actually getting to the
solution and are they are they taking
things all the way to full polish when
there's unknowns that they should be
addressing first so it also lets you
evaluate sequencing decisions that the
team is making in terms of which
problems do they take on in what order
and which problem which which scopes do
they allow to sort of sit at the top of
the hill knowing that there's some other
unknown that they better push up before
they they just do that that all of that
known work of getting the other things
downhill so there's a lot that can
happen there in an asynchronous way
where we avoid a lot of those sort of
painful and annoying conversations of
hey you know what's the status on this
how's that coming what's going on there
we're starting to run run out of time
fittingly the thing we haven't talked
about yet is how to decide when to stop
can you talk about wrapping up a project
first of all let's just remember that
we've created a whole constraint
structure now the team is working within
a six-week cycle or if they're not in
fixed cycles because you're a smaller
startup you're at least in an in a fixed
time box for this project the team was
given shaped work with a lot of latitude
for how they fill it in they are
responsible for making the trade-offs of
how they fill it in and we have the
circuit breakers so that if the project
goes overtime it doesn't automatically
get more time by default it gets
canceled and and of course the team is
uninterrupted so they actually have the
time to be successful the team is in
this situation where if they make the
right decisions they should be able to
finish and they should be able to ship
this thing because all the right
constraints are there to help them do
that but of course there's some forces
of nature that are always working
against you scope is always growing it's
not just that is the bad client or
there's the the clueless boss or
whatever it's who's constantly giving
you more work to do
scope grows by itself even when you have
really well shaped work because you just
get in there and you realize oh but we
could also do this and we could do that
and we could refactor this and this
should be better and that should be
better there's just no end to it you
know so the team needs to needs to be
able to constantly deal with all of
these these new things coming up that
they discover that they could be doing
and so we call that scope hammering and
it's a constant thing and the simplest
tool for that is is one that the team
can apply day after day after day and
it's just asking the question if we had
to ship tomorrow could we ship without
this thing or not so really just is it a
must-have or is it nice to have and then
we have a simple tool for that so any
task that the team comes up with or
discovers or bumps into when they add
that task to a to-do list for a scope
they mark it with a tilde in front to
indicate if it's a nice to have and the
important thing is that they they always
ask themselves the question so we really
expect our team's and we teach them and
encourage them and expect them to engage
with the scope you never just see things
and then and then add a task before you
add that task you ask yourself is
must have or not and and you need to be
tough about that that question and then
so we'll have a lot of work actually
with these little tilde s on the front
of the tasks and that indicates okay if
we have time later you know if we get
the main things done and we're satisfied
then we'll come back and reconsider this
so that's the first thing to helping us
actually finish the second thing is we
need to to set the right reference point
so that we can so that we can call what
we're doing a success
very often teams are working on a
project and they are constantly thinking
about well what would make it better and
so you're looking up to an ideal of
what's the best version of this and then
are we there yet what we want to do
instead is we want to look down to a
baseline and the baseline of performance
is what our customers or users doing
today without this thing so we've got
this work in a branch customers don't
have it what are they doing today what
are they not doing today cuz because
they don't have this and and then we
want to make that comparison back down
to what life is like without this thing
for the customer base instead of making
that comparison up and forward to the
even better version that we haven't
built yet and when we make that that
performance comparison from our
work-in-progress
down to the baseline then we can say to
ourselves aha this is definitely better
when it's not perfect and it has all
these flaws but it's definitely better
than what people have today you know or
it's better than nothing and from that
point of view it becomes easier to make
those tough calls and those tough
trade-offs to say what really is that
Mustang must have and what is that nice
to have and and make the call to ship it
great before we wrap up is there any
must-have must discuss things that we
haven't covered you'd like to talk about
yeah there's one thing I do want to
mention which is that there's different
phases of the work when you're working
on an entirely new product or if you are
working on a completely foreign
technical foundation so what I mean is
like if you're if you're working in a
language you've never used before or
some kind of a new technology that you
haven't used at all and you really
really don't have firm ground underneath
you this this sort of shape that build
process it does not work in that
scenario
there's sort of two phases when you when
you're first working on a brand new
product there's an early phase where you
don't actually know kind of how the main
features hang together so that so that
it's going to be viable and you don't
really know exactly what the correct
database model is going to be and and
the main modeling in the back end how
that should be architected we call it
R&D mode and production mode and R&D
mode we deal with it differently so it's
much more of a skunkworks type project
we're gonna have a very senior
programmer and an experienced designer
are gonna team up and they're not going
to shape something and then say now we
we we believe that this is a you know a
really good bet and then bet on it
because they're you just don't know
enough yet when you're starting brand
new on a brand new product you don't
have any established architecture that
you're working within to have that
certainty to bet on so instead we're
just gonna bet ass like a fixed amount
of time let's say six weeks and within
that time the goal isn't to build a
project to completion and then deploy it
instead there's going to be a few
tentpole features that the this sort of
skunk works team nose needs to get
figured out and then they're gonna be
firing tracer bullets and just building
things halfway up just building things
just just spiking enough to get some
certainty about the architecture then
once the architecture is the main points
of the architecture is settled and you
can say okay more or less this feature
lives over here and that's over here and
that's over here and this is how it all
hangs together then you can flip the
switch and you can move into production
mode and then because you have this sort
of solid ground of a settled
architecture that's where you can start
to do shaping and bedding where you say
I'm going to define this work for
another team to do you know when you're
in that are das it's it's it's normal
and natural and okay to work for like
two weeks and then scrap everything you
did and then and then do a totally
different approach because you just
don't have the firm ground underneath
you yet but you can't keep working like
that forever you need to get to a point
where you pour some concrete you make
some commitments on the foundation and
then from there now it's clear kind of
where load-bearing structures for future
features can go and then you're in a
place where you can shape something and
give it
other people to execute and and and you
can expect them to be successful in ship
at the end of that so I just want to
call that out that the way we deal with
shaping is different in those two phases
in the R&D phase shaping and building
get mixed together in a blurry mix with
the skunk works team you know just
spiking out stuff to figure out what the
right basic architecture is versus in
production mode we can have these very
discrete steps where we're shaping
getting to a point of a potential bet
making the bet and then expecting the
team to execute on that I think there's
something else you mentioned in the
towards the end of your book about
onboarding like how to begin shaping up
yeah maybe share some similarities with
the R&D phase where you just you just
want to take a few maybe one team and
get them started did you want to talk
about that sure we've seen a few
different cases for how people get
started and it can depend you know and a
lot of factors like how big the company
is and what your role is in it so of
course we've seen we've seen some people
just start whole-hog where there's the
founder learns about the method and and
and kind of relates to a lot of the
struggles that we talked about and
they're like you know what we're gonna
work this way and then they just call it
and and they switch to everything we we
have seen that in other cases there's
been times where somebody in a more kind
of a CT overall starts to see all the
difficulties they have with the two-week
Sprint's and they started to think hmm
you know maybe we would be able to get
more meaningful work done if we had a
longer cycle and then they switched to
maybe like a six-week cycle but they
might not quite relate to the shaping
work immediately especially if they're
in is more of a CTO type role so what
will happen is they'll they'll find that
they have much more room to get
meaningful things done but then after
after some time then they'll start to
realize like oh if we shape the work
then we would have even better outcomes
with this new capacity that we have we
would be like putting the right work you
know into this 6-week box so I've seen
that where we start with cycles and go
into shaping from there I've also seen
it where somebody is more in a product
role or a senior design role and they
don't have control over the way that
resources get scheduled and kind of you
know how programmers spend their time so
what they do is they start by shaping a
project that has such clear
boundaries that they then can kind of go
around and shop that to people inside
the company and say look I've got this
really meaningful thing we can do and I
think that if we just had a team of
three we could get this thing released
in six weeks and it would be a big win
for us and people say oh look at that
I've never seen work I've never seen
work that was so so clear before I can
really see kind of what the end of this
looks like and what we're doing and not
doing
and then okay fine like let's let's
carve out those three people and and
then they get they have a lot of success
with it the project goes well and then
it's like okay let's do that again right
and then the question becomes kind of
how do we structure ourselves to repeat
that and then that leads you down a path
of putting cycles in place so that you
have sort of irregularity to the
availability of your resources and then
having a sort of routine of shaping so
that the work that you put into those
into those teams is is risk reduced so
so there's there's all kinds of
different starting points and it doesn't
have to be the whole business of once it
can be a single project it can be within
a single team you know if you have if
you have quite a lot of people it can
just be one team the important thing I
think is to first start having the
conversations with the team using the
language that the book gives you you can
start to talk about the shaping work
when you maybe didn't have a word for it
before and you can talk about what
happens when you don't shape you know
that meeting that you have that grooming
session when there's all kinds of
technical questions getting raised about
the work and you have mock-ups but you
don't have any good answers to the
technical questions and then everybody
feels a little bit queasy committing to
it knowing that there's too many
unknowns and everything's rushed and we
know what that's like so we can we can
use the language to talk about that or
we can talk about uphill versus downhill
work and what goes wrong when we keep
extending time on uphill work and stuff
like that or the difference between our
estimates versus our appetite and those
will start those will start
conversations that can be really
productive and then as you start to
identify where you can do better and
you've got this whole toolbox to reach
into you know whether it's cycles or
betting tables or pitches or whatever it
is you can figure out how to start to
assemble that into a product into a
process that makes sense for the for the
org structure you have in the current
scale you wrap where can our listeners
go to find the book and
to find more information or more
information about you and what you're
doing yeah so the the book is at
Basecamp calm slash shape-up and you can
read it online or you can download it as
a PDF and we're also gonna be working on
other formats so publishing on the web
has allowed us to to keep making changes
and fix this to it as we get feedback
and we'll be will be doing a print and
an audio book and ebook and stuff like
that down the road you can also sign up
there at Basecamp comm slash shape up to
get notified when those other formats
are ready and and then I'm I'm RJ s at
Twitter and you know if you want to see
updates on the book or commentary on
these topics that's sort of the that's
the main place where where I've been
posting those bits you have the
three-letter twitter handle huh yeah
it's there for a while well Rhino is
great having you on software engineering
radio thanks a lot I really appreciate
it for software engineering radio this
has been Nate black thanks for listening
thanks for listening to Nessie radio an
educational program brought to you by
Triple E software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at se - radio
net to provide feedback you can comment
on each episode on the website that will
reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or
through our slack channel at SC
radio.com you can also email us at team
@ SC - radio net this and all other
episodes of se radio is licensed under
Creative Commons license 2.5 thanks for
listening
[Music]